Leah: We can see by looking at the
different languages that can be learnt
that programming languages can be
used for the various functions that
computers and devices can perform.
Let's look at some of the terms that
are used in relation to different
types of language and programming.
Jack: Programming Paradigm
A programming paradigm doesn't
refer to a specific language
but rather to a way to program.
Some languages make it easy to write
in some paradigms, but not others.
Leah: Functional Programming
Functional programming languages
are based on mathematical functions
that use linear mathematical logic.
They work well with list processing
applications and large data analysis.
Jack: Object Oriented
The most popular programming languages
in the current arena as we have
seen, are known as 'object oriented'.
This means that the language
is organised around groupings
of data also called 'objects'.
These types of languages are therefore
often easy to manipulate, reuse and
scale, making them quite versatile
and ideal for structuring software.
So, let's look at the differences
between object oriented languages and
procedural programming and the reasons
most popular modern languages have
adopted the Object Oriented style.
Leah: Procedural programming
In procedural programming, a program is
divided into small parts also known as
'functions' [routines and sub routines].
This is often referred to as inline
programming taking a form of top-down
approach, solving problems from the top
of the code to the bottom, through a
series of steps that must be carried out.
These procedures are broken down through
'functional decomposition' until a sub
procedure is simple enough to be solved.
If, however, edits are needed, then
every line of code associated to the
original change needs to be edited too.
This makes it harder to locate all the
related elements that need to be altered.
Procedural programming does not
also, have a proper method for
hiding data so it is less secure.
Adding data and function is not
easy and the function is often more
important than the data itself.
Examples of languages used in
procedural programming are FORTRAN,
ALGOL, COBOL, BASIC, Pascal and C.
Jack: Object Oriented Programming
Object Oriented Programming
is a programming model based
around the principle of objects.
It uses collections of objects to pass
on messages when called upon, to request
specific services or information.
Objects contain data in the
form of attributes and code.
Object oriented programming has
access specifiers such as private,
public, protected and this ability
to hide data means it is more secure.
Adding data is easier as new objects can
inherit characteristics from existing ones
making adjustment of programs simpler.
Data is more important than the
function and it is based more
on the real-world environment.
This form of programming
is a bottom-up approach.
Many object-oriented programming
languages will dump or destroy
unused objects, freeing up system
memory which enables systems to
run faster and more effectively.
Examples of languages used in
object-oriented programming
are Java, JavaScript, C++,
C#, Python, PHP, Ruby, etc.
As you can see by the list of
languages, we have looked at already
they all fall into the category
of object oriented languages.